Six months ago, I got an email
قبل ستة أشهر ، وصلني بريد إلكتروني
from a man in Israel
من رجل في إسرائيل
who had read one of my books,
كان قد قرأ أحد كتبي ،
and the email said,
يقول في البريد ،
"You don't know me,
" أنت لا تعرفني ،
but I'm your 12th cousin."
لكني قريبك من الدرجة 12 . "
And it said, "I have a family tree
يقول أيضاً ، " لدي شجرة عائلة
with 80,000 people on it, including you,
فيها 80000 شخص ، بمن فيهم أنت
Karl Marx,
وكارل ماركس ،
and several European aristocrats."
والعديد من النبلاء الأوربيين . "
Now I did not know what to make of this.
حينها لم أدري ماذا أفعل .
Part of me was like, okay,
جزء مني كان يقول ، حسناً
when's he going to ask me to wire
متى سيطلب مني أن أحوّل
10,000 dollars to his Nigerian bank, right?
10000 دولار إلى حسابه بنكه النيجيري ، أليس كذلك ؟
I also thought, 80,000 relatives,
كذلك تساءلت ، 80000 قريب ،
do I want that?
هل أريد هذا ؟
I have enough trouble with some of the ones
لدي مشاكل بالفعل مع بعض الأقارب
I have already.
الحاليين .
And I won't name names, but you know who you are.
لا أريد ذكر اسماء ، لكنكم تعرفون أنفسكم .
But another part of me said, this is remarkable.
لكن جزء آخر مني كان يقول ، هذا رائع .
Here I am alone in my office, but I'm not alone at all.
ها أنا وحيدٌ في مكتبي ، لكني لست وحيداً على الإطلاق .
I'm connected to 80,000 people around the world,
أنا متصل بـ 80000 قريب حول العالم ،
and that's four Madison Square Gardens
أي أربعة أضعاف حدائق ساحة ماديسون
full of cousins.
مملوءة بالأقارب .
and some of them are going to be irritating,
والبعض الآخر قد يكون مزعج ،
but they're all related to me.
لكنهم كلهم مرتبطين بي .
So this email inspired me to dive into genealogy,
لقد ألهمني هذا البريد بالغوص في علم الأنساب ،
which I always thought was a very staid and proper field,
الذي كنت أعتقد دائماً أنه مجال رزين ومناسب ،
but it turns out it's going through a fascinating
وقد اتضح لي أنه يمر بثورة مبهرة
revolution, and a controversial one.
ومثيرة للجدل .
Partly, this is because of DNA and genetic testing,
جزئياً ، بسبب الـحمض النووي والفحص الوراثي ،
but partly, it's because of the Internet.
وجزئياً بسبب الإنترنت .
There are sites that now take
هناك الآن مواقع على الإنترنت
the Wikipedia approach to family trees,
تتخذ أسلوب الويكيبيديا مع شجرات العائلة ،
collaboration and crowdsourcing,
بالتعاون والمصدر الجماعي ،
and what you do is,
والذي عليك فعله هو ،
you load your family tree on,
أن تقوم برفع شجرة عائلتك ،
and then these sites search
وبعدها تقوم هذه المواقع بالبحث
to see if the A.J. Jacobs in your tree
لترى هل جيكوبز الذي في شجرتك
is the same as the A.J. Jacobs in another tree,
هو نفسه الموجود في شجرة آخرى ،
and if it is, then you can combine,
في حال كان هو ، عندها تستطيع دمجه ،
and then you combine and combine and combine
ثم تدمج بإستمرار
until you get these massive,
إلى أن تحصل على هذه الشجرات العملاقة
mega-family trees
للعوائل الضخمة
with thousands of people on them,
والتي تحوي آلاف الأشخاص فيها ،
or even millions.
بل حتى الملايين .
I'm on something on Geni called
انا اعمل على مشروع في موقع الأنساب "جيني" يسمى
the world family tree,
شجرة عائلة العالم
which has no less than a jaw-dropping
وهذا شيء أكثر من رائع
75 million people.
75 مليون شخص
So that's 75 million people connected by blood
اذاً هناك 75 شخص متصلين بالدم
or marriage, sometimes both.
او الزواج وأحياناً كلاهما
I'm on it. Many of you are on it,
أنا متواجد فيها ، كثير منكم ايضاً
whether you know it or not,
سواء كنتم تعلمون ام لا ،
and you can see the links.
و يمكنكم ان ترون الروابط
Here's my cousin Gwyneth Paltrow.
هنا قريبتي جوينيث بالترو
She has no idea I exist,
هي لا تملك ادنى فكرة عني ،
but we are officially cousins.
لكننا بصورة رسمية اقرباء
We have just 17 links between us.
نملك فقط 17رابط يفصل بيننا
And there's my cousin Barack Obama.
وهناك قريبي باراك اوباما
(Laughter)
(ضحك )
And he is my aunt's fifth great-aunt's husband's
وهو ابن الاخ السابع لزوجة عمتي
father's wife's seventh great-nephew,
ابو زوج العمة الخامسة لعمتي
so practically my old brother.
إذاً عملياً اخي الأكبر
And my cousin, of course,
وقريبي في نفس الوقت ، طبعاً
the actor Kevin Bacon --
الممثل كيفين بيكون
(Laughter) —
( ضحك )
who is my first cousin's twice removed's
وهو إبن عمي من الدرجة الثانية
wife's niece's husband's first cousin once removed's
قريب لأبن عم زوجتي من الدرجة الأولي
niece's husband.
زوجة ابن عمي
So six degrees of Kevin Bacon,
إذاً قريبي من الدرجة السادسة
plus or minus several degrees.
بالإضافة او ناقصاً عدة درجات (ضحك)
have famous people and historical figures
يملكون مشاهير وشخصيات تاريخية
in your tree, because we are all connected,
في شجرتكم العائلية ، لأن كلنا متصلين في النهاية
and 75 million may seem like a lot,
و 75 مليون قد يبدو انه عدد ضخم
but in a few years, it's quite likely
لكن في سنوات قليلة ، من المحتمل جدا
we will have a family tree
ان نملك شجرة عائلية
with all, almost all, seven billion people on Earth.
تحتوي تقريبا على جميع سكان العالم ، سبعة مليارات شخص
But does it really matter?
لكن هل حقاً هذا يهم ؟
What's the importance?
اين الأهمية ؟
And I do think it is important,
انا اعتقد انه مهم ،
and I'll give you five reasons why, really quickly.
و سأطرح خمسة اسباب ، على عجلة
First, it's got scientific value.
الأول : له قيمة علمية
This is an unprecedented history of the human race,
هذا شيء لم يسبق له مثيل في تاريخ الجنس البشري
and it's giving us valuable data
وسيزودنا بحقائق مهمة
about how diseases are inherited,
عن كيفية توارث الأمراض
how people migrate,
وكيفية هجرة الناس
and there's a team of scientists at MIT right now
وهناك فريق علمي في معهد ماساتشوستس للتقنية حالياً
studying the world family tree.
يدرس الشجرة العائلية للعالم
Number two, it brings history alive.
الثاني : إننا نعيد إحياء التاريخ
I found out I'm connected to Albert Einstein,
اكتشفت صلة قرابه بيني وبين البرت إنشتاين
so I told my seven-year-old son that,
وبالتالي اخبرت ولدي ذو السبع سنين ذلك
and he was totally engaged.
وحازت الفكرة إهتمامه
Now Albert Einstein is not some dead white guy
الآن البرت إنيشتاين ليس مجرد شخص ميت ذو بشرة بيضاء
with weird hair.
مع شعر غريب
He's Uncle Albert. (Laughter)
إنه العم إلبرت . (ضحك)
And my son wanted to know,
وإبني يريد ان يعرف ،
"What did he say? What is E = MC squared?"
ماذا قال ؟ وما تعني E=mc² ؟
Also, it's not all good news.
أيضاً ، ليس كلها اخبار جيدة
I found a link to Jeffrey Dahmer, the serial killer,
وجد صلة قرابة تجمعني بجيفري دامر ، قاتل متسلسل
but I will say that's on my wife's side.
لكن هذا قي جهة اقارب زوجتي
(Laughter) (Applause)
( ضحك )
So I want to make that clear. Sorry, honey.
اريد جعل هذا واضحاُ ، آسف عزيزتي
Number three, interconnectedness.
الثالث :الترابط
We all come from the same ancestor,
نحن جميعاً يجمعنا جد واحد
and you don't have to believe the literal Bible version,
ولا يجب عليك تصديق نسخة الإنجيل
but scientists talk about Y chromosomal Adam
لكن العلماء تحدثوا عن كرومسومات آدم
and mitochondrial Eve,
وميتوكندريا حواء
and these were about 100,000 to 300,000 years ago.
وهذه كانت قبل 100,000 إلى 300,00 سنة
We all have a bit of their DNA in us.
جميعنا نملك جزء من حمضهم النووي بداخلنا
They are our great-great-great-great-great-great --
هم كانوا اجداد لأجدادنا
continue that for about 7,000 times --
ويستمر إلى 7000 مرة ـــ
grandparents,
اجدادنا ،
and so that means we literally all are
وهذا يعني حرفياً أننا جميعاً
biological cousins as well,
علمياً اقرباء ايضا
and estimates vary, but probably
وتختلف التقديرات ، لكن احتمال
the farthest cousin you have on Earth
أن ابعد قريب لك في الأرض
is about a 50th cousin.
هو قريبك من الدرجة الخمسين
Now, it's not just ancestors we share, descendants.
الآن , نحن لا نتشارك فقط في الأسلاف ، الأحفاد
If you have kids, and they have kids,
إذا كنت تملك أولاد . ثم انجبوا اولاد
look how quickly the descendants accumulate.
انظر كيف بسرعة يتراكم الأحفاد
So in 10, 12 generations,
إذا في 10 ـ 12 جيل
you're going to have thousands of offspring,
ستكون ذريتك بالآلاف
and millions of offspring.
والملايين
Number four, a kinder world.
الرابع : عالم ألطف
Now, I know that there are family feuds.
الآن ، أعلم ان هناك خلافات عائلية
I have three sons, so I see how they fight.
املك ثلاث ابناء ، واراهم يتضاربون
But I think that there's also a human bias
لكن ارى أن هناك محاباة إنسانية
to treat your family a little better than strangers.
بأن تتعامل مع عائلتك بشكل أفضل قليلاً من تعاملك مع الغرباء
I think this tree is going to be bad news for bigots,
اتوقع بأن هذه الشجرة ستكون خبراً سيئاً للمتعصبين
that they are cousins with thousands of people
أنهم أقرباء مع آلاف من البشر
in whatever ethnic group they happen
من أي مجموعة عرقية
to have issues with,
يملكون مشكلة معها
and I think you look back at history,
وأنا اعتقد ذا رجعت للتاريخ
and a lot of the terrible things we've done to each other
هناك العديد من الأشياء السيئة التي فعلناها لبعضنا البعض
is because one group thinks another group is sub-human,
لأن هناك مجموعة تظن أن الباقين دون البشر
and you can't do that anymore.
ولا تستطيع فعل ذلك بعد الآن .
We're not just part of the same species.
لسنا فقط افراداً من نفس الجنس
We're part of the same family.
نحن أشخاص من عائلة واحدة
We share 99.9 percent of our DNA.
نحن نتشارك 99.9% من حمضنا النووي
Now the final one is number five,
الآن و أخيراً السبب الخامس
a democratizing effect.
تأثير الديمقراطية ،
Some genealogy has an elitist strain,
بعض الأنساب يملكون سلالة نخبوية
like people say, "Oh, I'm descended
مثل الأشخاص القائلين, اوه ، انا منحدر
from Mary Queen of Scots
من سلالة ماري ملكة الإستكلنديين
and you're not, so you cannot join my country club."
وأنت لا ، لذا لا يمكنك المشاركة في النادي
But that's really going to be hard to do now,
لكن ذلك سيكون من الصعوبة عمله حالياُ
because everyone is related.
لأن كل شخص ذا صلة
I'm descended from Mary Queen of Scots --
انا من منحدر من سلالة ماري ملكة الإستكلنديين،
by marriage, but still.
من جهة زوجتي ، لكن لا يزال ...
in the history of family,
في تاريخ العوائل
because it's changing so fast.
لأنه سريع التغير.
There is gay marriage and sperm donors
الآن هنالك زواج الشواذ ومتبرعين بالسائل المنوي
and this makes some of my more conservative cousins
وهذا يجعل بعض أقاربي المحافظين
a little nervous,
قلقين قليلاً
but I actually think it's a good thing.
لكن فعلاً اعتقد انه شيء جيد
I think the more inclusive the idea of family is,
أعتقد انه كلما تنوعت فكرة العائلة
the better,
ذلك أفضل
because then you have more potential caretakers,
لان ذلك يعني المزيد من إمكانيات الرعاية الصحية
and as my aunt's eighth cousin twice removed
وكما ابنة عم عمتي من الدرجة الثامنة
Hillary Clinton says --
هيلاري كلينتون قالت:
(Laughter) —
( ضحك )
it takes a village.
ان الامور تتغير
So I have all these hundreds and thousands,
(ضحك )
I thought, what can I do with this information?
فكرت ، ماذا يمكن أن أفعل بهذه المعلومة ؟
And that's when I decided,
وحينها قررت ،
why not throw a party?
مالذي يمنعنا من إقامة حفلة ؟
So that's what I'm doing.
إذاً هذا ما أفعل
And you're all invited.
و كلكم مدعويين
Next year, next summer,
السنة القادمة ، الصيف القادم
I will be hosting what I hope is
سأقوم بإقامة ما آمل أن يكون
the biggest and best family reunion in history.
أكبر و أفضل اجتماع عائلي في التاريخ
(Applause)
( تصفيق )
Thank you. I want you there.
شكرآ لكم ، اريدكم هناك
I want you there.
أريدكم هناك
It's going to be at the New York Hall of Science,
سوف تكون في قاعة العلوم في نيويورك
which is a great venue,
وهو مكان رائع
but it's also on the site of the former World's Fair,
لكنه أيضاً في مكان المعرض العالمي السابق
which is, I think, very appropriate,
و هو ، اعتقد ، انه مناسب جداً
because I see this as a family reunion
لأني أراه كأجتماع عائلي
meets a world's fair.
يتلقون نوعا من العدالة في الكوكب
There's going to be exhibits and food, music.
سوف يكون هناك معارض ، طعام ، موسيقى
Paul McCartney is 11 steps away,
بول مكارتني على بعد 11 خطوة
so I'm hoping he brings his guitar.
لذا أنا آمل ان يحضر القيثارة معه
He hasn't RSVP'd yet, but fingers crossed.
هو لم يرد بعد ، لكن أتمنى
And there is going to be a day of speakers,
وسوف يكون هناك يوم للمتحدثين
of fascinating cousins.
لأقارب رائعون
It's early, but I've already,
إنه مبكر و لكن
I've got some lined up.
أملك بعض الخطط
Cass Sunstein, my cousin who is perhaps
كاس سانستين ، قريبي وهو من
the most brilliant legal scholar, will be talking.
افضل عباقرة البحث القانوني ، سيكون من المتحدثين
He was a former member of the Obama administration.
هو كان عضو سابق تحت إدارة اوباما
And on the other side of the political spectrum,
و في الجانب الآخر من الإنتماء السياسي
George H.W. Bush, number 41, the father,
جورج بوش الأب الرئيس 41
he has agreed to participate,
هو وافق على المشاركة
and Nick Kroll, the comedian,
و الكوميدي نيك كرول ،
and Dr. Oz, and many more to come.
ودكتور أوز ، و غيرهم كثير
I want you guys there,
اريدكم يا رفاق في المحفل
and I invite you to go to GlobalFamilyReunion.org
وأدعوكم لزيارة الموقع
because these are big issues, family and tribe,
لأن هذه قضايا مهمة و العائلة والقبيلة
and I don't know all the answers,
وانا لا املك جميع الأسئلة
but I have a lot of smart relatives,
لكن أملك العديد من الأقارب الأذكياء
including you guys,
بما فيهم أنتم يارفاق
so together, I think we can figure it out.
لذلك معاَ ، اعتقد أنه يمكننا معرفتها
Only together can we solve these big problems.
فقط مع بعض يمكننا حل أعظم المشاكل
So from cousin to cousin,
إذا من قريب لآخر
I thank you. I can't wait to see you.
أشكركم ، لا أستطيع الصبر لأراكم
Goodbye.
وداعاً